<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Church-pageantry display'd, or, Organ-worship, arraign'd and condemn'd, as inconsistent with the revelation and worship of the Gospel, the sentiments of the ancient fathers, the Church of England, and several eminent divines, both Protestants and Papists. By Eugenius Junior - in answer to a letter about organs.</title>
            <author>Owen, James, 1654-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O706A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25513</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834851</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834851</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39444</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53658)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39444)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1291:6, 1768:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Church-pageantry display'd, or, Organ-worship, arraign'd and condemn'd, as inconsistent with the revelation and worship of the Gospel, the sentiments of the ancient fathers, the Church of England, and several eminent divines, both Protestants and Papists. By Eugenius Junior - in answer to a letter about organs.</title>
                  <author>Owen, James, 1654-1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for A. Baldwin, at the Oxford-Arms in Warwick-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identified on UMI microfilm (Early English books, 1641-1700) reel 1291 as Wing (2nd ed.) O728.  Wing number cancelled in Wing (CD-ROM, 1996).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library (reel 1291), and the Bodleian Library (reel 1768).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church music --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39444:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Church-Pageantry DISPLAY'D: OR, <hi>Organ-Worſhip,</hi> Arraign'd and Condemn'd, As inconſiſtent with the Revelation and Worſhip of the Goſpel, the Sentiments of the Ancient Fathers, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſeveral Eminent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, both <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>That it may pleaſe Thee to bring into the Way of Truth all ſuch as have Erred, and are Deceived.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We beſeech Thee to hear us good Lord.</hi> Amen!</p>
            <q>The beſt Muſical Inſtrument for God's Praiſe is an upright Heart. <bibl>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Cowper</hi>'s <hi>Works</hi> Printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1621. Page 371.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Eugenius Junior</hi> — In ANSWER to a Letter about ORGANS.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nitimur in vetitum ſemper cupimuſque negata.</l>
               <l>Is any Merry? Let him ſing Pſalms.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>A. Baldwin,</hi> at the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:39444:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39444:2"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Introduction. The Patriarchal and Old Teſtament-Church about Three Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Years without Organ-Worſhip. An Account of other Inſtrumental Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick us'd in Divine Praiſes. Organs and other Muſical Inſtruments under the Legal Diſpenſation, Parts of the Ceremonial Law, inſtituted by Divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; are not obligatory under the Goſpel, no more than other Branches of the Ceremonial Law, which by the Confeſſion of Organical Advocates are abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated.</p>
            </argument>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THERE's no Requeſt of yours, but is equivolent to a Command with me: Whereas in your Letter to the 20th. Current you earneſtly crav'd my Sentiments about the uſe of Church-Muſick; becauſe a Friend of yours was going to erect a Pair of Organs in his Parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al-Church: I have comply'd with your Deſires, and in the following Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations have deliver'd my own Thoughts, and the Judgment of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others, touching it's unlawfulneſs under the Evangelical Oeconomy.</p>
            <p>Before I go on, I muſt beg the favour of you, as to give Place to calm and ſober Thoughts, and impartially to weigh the force of my Evidence: And (in order to that) I hope you'll be ſo juſt as to read over the whole Eſſay, before you proceed to a judicial definitive Cenſure. I am perſwaded you are of a candid Temper, and therefore I can the more freely communicate my Sentiments to you; and that I may the more effectually ſet the Affair in debate in it's true Light, I'll begin with the firſt Riſe and Uſe of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick and Muſical Devotions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Twas about Three Thouſand Years after the Creation, before any <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> were us'd in Divine Worſhip, That they were invented in the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the World, we readily grant. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.21. <hi>Jubal, he was the Father of all ſuch as handle Harp and Organ;</hi> but if one of the Poſterity of <hi>Bloody Cain</hi> was the Contriver of theſe paltry ſidling Pipes, will it therefore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that their uſe in Sacred Services was equally Ancient, with their firſt Invention? But it's doubtful, whether the Organs mention'd in this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be the ſame with ours, for the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for Organs which comes from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>luſit, adamavit,</hi> ſignifies <hi>quodvis inſtrumentum Muſicum, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi amabile dictum.</hi> Schindl. The <hi>Chaldee</hi> renders it, <hi>he was Maſter of all that Play on the Pſaltery, and knew Muſick:</hi> And the <hi>Greek</hi> Verſion reads it, <hi>this was he that ſhow'd the Pſaltry and the Harp,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:39444:3"/>
            <p> We have no Account of 'm as us'd in the Devotions of the <hi>Antediluvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Patriarchs, and 'twas about Seven Hundred Years after the Deluge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any ſort of Inſtrumental Muſick was us'd in Divine Worſhip. The firſt remarkable Inſtance that occurs, we have in <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.20, 21. Where it's ſaid, that <hi>Miriam the Propheteſs took a Timbrel in her Hand, and all the Women went after her with Timbrels and with Dances.</hi> There are Three Things that ſhew the invalidity of this Inſtance, in reference to the Point in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate (1.) You muſt Note, that this Woman was a Propheteſs, and what ſhe did was by an extraordinary impulſe; now Sir, when any of our Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Friends are actuated by a Prophetick Spirit, e'en let 'm uſe all the Cymbals, Timbrels, Tabrets, and Harps, upon the Terreſtrial Globe, and ſpare not, and I do aſſure you I'll never interrupt their Muſical Mirth; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let 'm ſtay till then. (2.) You muſt obſerve, that theſe were Women who <hi>plaid</hi> — and <hi>ſung</hi> — but <hi>Paul</hi> has been ſo kind to the Female Sex in our Days as to tye their Tongues at Church; tho' now and then notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his Apoſtolical Injunction many of 'm will have their full ſhare in <hi>iouncing</hi> and <hi>racketting</hi> David<hi>'s Pſalms,</hi> and be as clamorous in their Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as any of their Maſculine Neighbours; and therefore, if you're inclin'd to follow the <hi>Miriamite Pattern,</hi> you may ſoon find a parcel of brisk ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Girls for the Purpoſe without going as far as <hi>Billingſgate</hi> for 'm. (3.) Theſe Muſical-Women <hi>danced</hi> at the ſame time, ſo that Sir, you may ſee without the help of a pair of Canonical Spectacles, that <hi>Dancing</hi> in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip is of the ſame Age with Inſtrumental Muſick: A cap'ring De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion can pretend to as great Antiquity in the Church as any ſort of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental Muſick. And therefore, I know no Reaſon why you ſhou'd graciouſly receive the <hi>Muſical Part</hi> of the Old Service into the Church, and utterly reject the <hi>Dancing part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It's acknowledged that Organs and other Inſtruments of Muſick were Parts of the Ceremonial Law, or things peculiar to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Pedagogy, as Circumciſion, Paſſover, Sacrifices, Trumpets, Cymbals, were, Now if theſe and other Parts of the Legal Ceremonies are perfectly aboliſht, how comes it to paſs that Organs are continu'd? Why ſhou'd not the ſame Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments conclude againſt the Eccleſiaſtical Uſe of Organs, as conclude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church-uſe of other <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Muſical Inſtruments? Why ſhou'd the worſhipful Organs (forſooth) be readmitted into the Boſom of the Church, when other famous Inſtruments of Muſick are totally excluded? What war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant have you to reſtore and retain one Part of the Ceremonial Law more than another Part? Why a pair of Organs and not a brace of Timbrels? I believe neither you nor the Parſon wou'd Conſent to have the <hi>Jewiſh Harps, Dances, Tabrets, Trumpets, Cymbals,</hi> and <hi>Pſalteries,</hi> us'd in the Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and yet all theſe may be warrantably introduc'd into our Church, if
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39444:3"/>your Arguments for Organs hold Water. Pray good Sir, e'en let's have a parcel of Eccleſiaſtical-Trumpeters, Church-Dancers, Canonical-Harpers and Tinkling-Cymbaliſts, as well as a cumberſome Herd of expenceful jovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Organiſts. The <hi>Greek</hi> Churches<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur Lortie <hi>de Coen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om.</hi> p. 1. Cap. 6.</note> have upbraided the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> for uſing a <hi>Roaſted Lamb</hi> in the Lord's Supper, becauſe 'twas Part of the Ceremonial-Law: But I'll not inſiſt upon the monſtrous Effects of Superſtitious Love and Teſty Zeal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both of 'm are Blind; which (if you'll believe <hi>Scarron</hi>) made <hi>Eneas</hi> once when he went to Sacrifice, miſtake a <hi>black curl'd Spaniel</hi> for a <hi>black Ram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But under the Law the Muſical Inſtruments in the Church were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Infallible Directions of Heaven, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.25. <hi>He ſet the Levites in the Houſe of the Lord, with Cymbals, with Pſalteries, and with Harps, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Command of David, and of Gad the Kings Seer, and Nathan the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, for ſo was the Command of the Lord by his Prophets.</hi> But pray Sir, where is your Command for Organical Worſhip under the Goſpel? You've neither the Command of God, nor of the King, nor of the Parliament, nor of any Convocation, nor of any Canon, or Rubrick, and yet maugre all theſe aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Powers, you'll be meddling with your Pipes and hank'ring after the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Fruit. <hi>Tho. Aquinas,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Nihil debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus aſſumere in Divinum cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Praeter ea quae nobis auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate traduntur. <hi>Aquin.</hi> Sum. Qu. <hi>91. Art. 1.</hi> Typ. Mand. Ven. <hi>MDLXXXVI</hi>
               </note> that grand Maſter of Church-Ceremonies; even he cou'd ſay, <hi>That nothing ought to be intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into the Divine Service, but what may be warranted by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Command.</hi> But leſt you ſhou'd take it as an Affront to be corrected by a Catholick Friend, while you have a Mother a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live; I'll therefore bring you under the righteous Sentence of her Maternal Cenſure. Saith She,<note n="†" place="margin">Homilies Serm. of good Works. <hi>Part 3. p. 38.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Such has been the corrupt Inclination of Man ever ſuperſtitiouſly given, to make new honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: of God, of his own Head, and then to have more Affection and Devotion to keep that, than to ſearch out God's Commandments and do 'm.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> us'd 'm by Divine Order, and therefore, they were bleſt for the great End they were deſign'd for, but that therefore God will bleſs 'm now to the ſame Ends, when they are not commanded, is ſuch a Conſequence that all the Eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of the Organical Cauſe can never make good. What they did was the matter of a Divine Command, but being Ceremonial, 'twas abrogated by the Death of Chriſt, and therefore can't bind us under the Goſpel. Upon which account you muſt produce ſome new Proof, Order, or Commiſſion, or be Content to own your ſelves guilty of adding the Traditions of ſinful Men to the Sacred Canon. Becauſe the ſtiff-necked <hi>Jews</hi> of Old us'd Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, Pſalteries, Trumpets and Cymbals, purſuant to the Heavenly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, may you therefore do't now without a Command? This is moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39444:4"/>Logick, and it may be, may paſs for good arguing among a prophane Crew of ſinging Boys and their paſſionate Admirers.</p>
            <p>We are not under the Law, but under the Goſpel. So the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſpeaks.<note n="‖" place="margin">Her Diſcourſe about the Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> 
               <q>Chriſt's Goſpel is not a Ceremonial Law, but it's a Religion to ſerve God, not in Bondage of the Figure or Shadow, but in the Freedom of the Spirit.</q> That is, God is to be worſhipp'd now under the Goſpel in <hi>Spirit</hi> and in <hi>Truth,</hi> and not with the antiquated Ceremonies of the Law, ſuch as Cymbals, Organs, Sacrifices, Trumpets, Pſalteries — Now will any Man of common Sence plead for the uſe of a Thing as lawful under the Goſpel, becauſe 'twas made of Old a part of the Legal Service?</p>
            <p n="4">4. And it's certain, the New Teſtament makes no mention of any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental Muſick us'd in Divine Worſhip, and had it been really profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, wou'd the Holy Jeſus and his faithful Apoſtles paſs it by in ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Silence? Now Mr. <hi>Choriſter,</hi> I challenge you, or any of your Muſical Tribe to prove that ever Chriſt or his Apoſtles us'd, recommended, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged the Practice of Inſtrumental Muſick in the Sacred Aſſemblies of Chriſtians. It's remarkable in <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.23, 24, 25. that Chriſt does no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle till he turns out the <hi>Pipers</hi> and <hi>Fidlers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe, for once we humour your Fancy about Organs, will you then tell me, when and where you'll ſtop? If this be allow'd, may you not by Parity of Reaſon introduce the whole Body of <hi>Romiſh, Paganiſh, Judaical</hi> and <hi>Mahometan</hi> Ceremonies into the Church? If you are empower'd to bring in ſo conſiderable a thing as a pair of Devotional Organs, why mayn't you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſame Power fill the Church with a great many more new fangl'd Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Superſtitions? And at this rate, why mayn't we expect a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Articles, and new Schemes of Religion ev'ry new Year? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpawning of Novel Creeds and equipping out of Organical Confeſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Spring.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:39444:4"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>No Organs in the Primitive Church. They were firſt introduc'd into the New Teſtament Church by <hi>Pope Vitalian</hi> about Six Hundred Years after Chriſt, their uſe in Divine Service a Popiſh Practice in the Opinion of ſome Church-Men. Many of Opinion, they were not Churchify'd as ſoon as <hi>Vitalian</hi>'s Time. For there were no Organs in <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> in <hi>Aquinas</hi>'s Time, which was about Five Hundred Years ago. The Fathers, as <hi>Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, Iſidore, P. Theodoret, Ambroſe, Auſtiu</hi> — againſt the uſe of Organs in the Church.</p>
            </argument>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">1. IF what is wanting in the Sacred Text cou'd be made good by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Primitive Records, I ſhou'd not have attended this Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Buſineſs. I muſt needs ſay, that I owe the <hi>Fathers of the Church</hi> the Debt of an Honourable Memory; and therefore, if you had fled for Refuge into the abſtruſe receptacles of venerable Antiquity, I wou'd not have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd to haunt you out of your Burroughs; but upon a little ſearch into the Ancient Eccleſiaſtical Regiſters, you'll ſoon find that the <hi>Primo</hi>-Primitive-Chriſtians never made uſe of Organs in their Applications to the Heavenly Throne.</p>
            <p>The Ancient Fathers in their Writings are wholly ſilent; they give us not the leaſt hint that they approv'd of or had Organical Worſhip in the Church; but we have a new Generation of Pipers that are wiſer than their Fore-Fathers, and able to fathom the <hi>Indian Gulph,</hi> and if need be, reach the twinkling Stars with a <hi>Jacob</hi>'s <hi>Staff.</hi> Theſe are the evaporating Wits of the Age with whom alone (if you'll believe 'm) the Chryſtal Springs of Knowledge dwell. No doubt, but theſe Muſical Gentlemen drew their firſt breath in <hi>Tempe</hi> or <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> and had <hi>Appollo</hi> himſelf for their Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and the Harmonious Spheres for Nurſes; for their firſt and laſt Notes are nothing elſe, but <hi>Liſpt Meeter</hi> and <hi>Caſtalian Lays.</hi> But ſee how this ſid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling humour draws me out o'th' way.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Say ſome, 'twas about Six Hundred Years after Chriſt before Organs were introduc'd into the Chriſtian Church. The<note n="†" place="margin">Tandem <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 666.</hi> pleno numero Beſtiae, <hi>Apoc. 13.</hi> Cantum Latinum cum Organis Eccleſiae a <hi>Vitalino</hi> Pontifice ſuſceperunt miſſamq deinde. <hi>Magdeb.</hi> Centur. Cent. <hi>7. Cap. 6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Centuria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> tells us, <hi>That at laſt in the Year Six Hundred Sixty Six, in the full number of the Beaſt in</hi> Revel. 13th. <hi>the Churches receiv'd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39444:5"/>Latin ſinging with Organs from Pope</hi> Vitalian, <hi>and from thence began to ſay La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Maſs, and to ſet up Altars with Idolatrous Images.</hi>—And of this Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are <hi>Balaeus, Platina</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Plat. in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</note> and others. You may Note hence, that this Theatrical pompous ſort of Worſhip was firſt hatcht at <hi>Rome,</hi> where a great many other Eccleſiaſtical Gewgaws and Gibble-Gabbles have been invented; and had no meaner Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it's Original, than a Soveraign <hi>Pontiff,</hi> and he none of the beſt of the <hi>Purple Order,</hi> for by M. <hi>Prideaux</hi> he's rank'd in the Claſs of uſurping <hi>Nimrods.</hi> And beſides we muſt obſerve, that theſe Organs were introduc'd into Church in the Time of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Darkneſs, and were accompany'd with <hi>Latin Service</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous Images</hi> —.</p>
            <p>And, that this ſort of Organical Devotion looks like that of <hi>Rome,</hi> I Appeal to the Reverend<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 11. 17.</note> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> the preſent <hi>Rector</hi> of <hi>All Saints</hi> — in <hi>Colcheſter</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> who expreſſeth himſelf thus — <q>His Cope, his Hood, his Surplice, his Rochet, his cringing Worſhip, his Altars with Candles on 'm, his Bag-pipes or Organs, and in ſome Places Viols and Violins, and ſinging Boys are ſo very like Popery, that (ſaith he) I proteſt when I came in 1660. from beyond Sea to <hi>Paul</hi>'s and <hi>White-Hall,</hi> I cou'd ſcarce think my ſelf to be in <hi>England,</hi> but in <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Portugal</hi> again, I ſaw ſo little dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference but that their Service was in <hi>Latin</hi> and ours in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but leſs intelligible and edifying by Reaſon of the inarticulate <hi>Boatus</hi> and bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the alternate Jabberings and Mouthings of the People, whilſt all of 'm read half the Pſalms with a noiſe as confus'd as the rumbling Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; that any Man in the World that had ſeen <hi>High Maſs</hi> beyond Sea, muſt ſay, that the Contrivance of both was to keep People in Ignorance, <hi>Bellarmines</hi> Mother of Devotion.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Some others are of Opinion, that the uſe of Organs in the Chriſtian Church was not ſo early as this Popes Time: For, long after that; Organs were unknown in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany. Marianus Scotus</hi> tells us, they were firſt ſent of a Token to King <hi>Pepin</hi> in <hi>France; Aventinus</hi> gives the ſame Account, but adds, that they came not into any Church in <hi>France</hi> till the Year 828. when by the Induſtry of a <hi>Venetian Prieſt</hi> they were there ſet up. Church-Muſick was not introduc'd into the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches before the Time of <hi>Ludovicus Pius</hi> about the Year 840. One <hi>Georgius</hi> a <hi>Greek</hi> Prieſt, who was recommended to the Emperour by <hi>Count Baldric</hi> perſwaded him to admit into the Church<note n="†" place="margin">Aimon. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach. de Geſtis. <hi>Franc.</hi> lib. <hi>4.</hi> Cap. <hi>114.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>inuſitatam adhuc in regno Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum melodiam.</hi> But <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith, there were no Organs us'd in the Church, in his Time, which was about the Twelfth Century. Thus you ſee, tho' the Learned vary in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they give of their Original, yet they all agree they were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39444:5"/>not us'd in Chriſtian Aſſemblies for ſeveral hundred Years after Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As to the Fathers, it's plain, that they accounted Organs and other Muſical Inſtruments in Divine Worſhip, as Parts of the Old Ceremonial Law, and ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted only to the Infant State of the Church, and therefore no way Congruous to the ſpirituality of Goſpel-Services; this will more plainly appear, by conſidering the ſubſequent Paſſages collected out of 'm.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) We'll begin with <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>— Juſt. Martyr. <hi>ad Orth. Queſt.</hi> 107.</note>, who Dy'd about the Year 164. He ſaith to this Purpoſe, <q>That in his Time there was only plain ſimple ſinging with the Voice us'd in the Church:</q> And he calls the uſe of Church Muſick under the Old Teſtament, <hi>a puerile carnal Service,</hi> or <hi>a Childiſh ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>— Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dag. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.</note> who Liv'd about the Year 196. ſaith, we're commanded to <hi>Praiſe God on the Pſaltery, that is on the Tongue, becauſe the Tongue is the Pſaltery of the Lord. Praiſe him with the Harp, that is, with the Mouth; Praiſe him with the loud tinkling Cymbal, that is, the Tongue.</hi> And a little further he ſaith, <hi>That then they made uſe only of one Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the peaceful Word with which they honour'd God.</hi> Note hence, (1.) That he look'd upon the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church-Muſick to be Typical, <hi>i. e.</hi> a reſemblance, to emblematize or ſhadow out that inward Melody — which ſhou'd be in Goſpel Times, ſo ſaith <hi>Junius,</hi> 
               <q>Of thoſe Things commanded by the Law, ſome were <hi>ſignificative</hi> of ſome future Thing: Others were <hi>peculiar</hi> to that Church; now (ſaith he) to make uſe of things which were <hi>ſignificative</hi> of ſome thing Future after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, is <hi>Wicked;</hi> and now to uſe thoſe things which were <hi>peculiar</hi> to that Church is <hi>ridiculous.</hi>
               </q> So that according to his Judgment the uſe of Church-Muſick under the Goſpel is either <hi>impious</hi> or <hi>ridiculous.</hi> (2.) <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> in ſome of's Writings, complains much of the decay of Zeal and of the Power of Godlineſs among Profeſſors in his Time, and yet I believe it ne'r enter'd into the Brains of the good Man, that a pair of Organs wou'd have been a Remedy for that growing Evil.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>— in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 144. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> who Di'd about the Year 407. ſaith, <q>That under the Old Teſtament, there were Organs by which Songs of Praiſe were offer'd up to God, but now in the ſtead of Organs we make uſe of the Body, the Members of which become a Pſaltery and a Harp—.</q> And in another Place<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſpeaking of Muſical Inſtruments in Gods Service, he ſaith, <hi>Let no Man deceive you, theſe appertain not to Chriſtians: Theſe are Alien to the Chriſtian Church; all theſe the Nations of the World ſeek after.</hi> Note hence, (1.) He aſſerts that Organs —
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39444:6"/>did not belong to <hi>Chriſtian Worſhip.</hi> Either he was erroneous in's Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or the Patrons of our melodious Organs are guilty of an unchriſtian Practice. But (2.) He makes thoſe to be <hi>deceivers of the People</hi> that intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Organs, or any other ſort of Inſtrumental Muſick into Church-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: Here's a heavy Charge, and ſome Body muſt be Guilty; either the Father of the Church, or the Eccleſiaſtical Organeer. You muſt either brand the good old Man for a lying Scribbler, or own Organical Worſhip to be a meer Cheat, and a Church Deluſion — <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum horum mavis accipe</hi> — (3.) He makes Organ-Worſhip to be a <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> Practice. This puts me in mind of what the Learned Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Orig. Sacr.</note> late Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> tells us out of <hi>Strabo,</hi> that the <hi>Corybantes</hi> of old <hi>in their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip danc'd about with their Cymbals, Pipes, Drums, and Arms, as if</hi> Bedlam <hi>had been broke looſe among 'm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">(4.) <hi>Iſidore Peluſiota,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſid. Pel.</hi> lib. 1. Ep. 457. <hi>in Pſ.</hi> 150. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who Liv'd about the beginning of the Fourth Century, ſaith, <q>If ye ſeek an Explication of that Muſick mention'd in Scripture, underſtand after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; <hi>viz.</hi> They prais'd God with the ſound of a Trumpet in Memory of the Reſurrection; which will be with a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. Praiſe him with the Pſaltery and Harp, that is, with the Tongue and Mouth. Praiſe him with Strings and Organs, that is, with the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and all the inward Parts.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="5">(5.) <hi>Theodoret,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. — Theod. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Serm.</hi> 7.</note> who flouriſh'd about the Year 430. after Chriſt, ſaith, <q>God indulged 'm (the <hi>Jews</hi>) the uſe of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Inſtruments, not that he was delighted with their Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, but ſo by little and little he put a ſtop to the deceit of Idols.</q> And in another Place, he ſaith to this Effect,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>— Comment. <hi>in Pſ.</hi> 32.2, 3.</note> that thoſe Muſical Inſtruments ſpoken of in the Old Teſtament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to us, if they're underſtood ſpiritually — <q>And we muſt render our ſelves an Harmonious Organ to God, and Praiſe him by the Inſtruments of all the Senſes.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="6">(6.) <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who Di'd <hi>Anno</hi> 397.<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Confeſs.</hi> IX. 7.</note> introduc'd the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Way of Singing at <hi>Milan,</hi> to divert the good People that watch'd with him in the Church, to prevent <hi>Juſtina, Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi>'s Mother, from delivering it to the <hi>Arians,</hi> whoſe Hereſie ſhe favour'd: And from <hi>Milan</hi> that more artificial way of ſinging ſpread through the <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern.</hi> Churches.</p>
            <p n="7">(7.) This melodious Singing did ſo tickle St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Ears, and cauſe in him ſuch a degree of carnal Delight, that the wiſhes 'twere laid aſide in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39444:6"/>Church,<note n="†" place="margin">— Ab auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus meis remc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veri velim at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ipſius Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae. <hi>Conf. X. 33.</hi>
               </note> and reckons it much ſafer to imitate the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> Way of ſinging in <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s Time, who made his <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> to ſound the Pſalm with ſo ſmall a turn of his Voice, <hi>ut pronuncianti vicinor eſſet quam canenti.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> If the more artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Way of Vocal Singing ſeem'd enſnaring to this devout Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what wou'd he have ſaid to our Modern Organical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts?</p>
            <p n="8">(8.) Add to all theſe the Account we have of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Worſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> When the Congregation was aſſembl'd they firſt read the Scriptures, and ſometimes other Writings, then Pray'd, and then Preach'd, and concluded with Prayer. In our Publick Aſſemblies ſaith<note n="†" place="margin">Scripturae le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur, Pſalmi canuntur, ad locutiones pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feruntur, &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titiones dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull.</hi> de Anima <hi>Cap. 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tertullian,</hi> (who Liv'd about the Year 202. after Chriſt) <hi>The Scriptures are Read, Pſalms are Sung, Sermons Preached, and Prayers preſented.</hi> Not a Word of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> nor of the <hi>Vitalian</hi> and <hi>Gregorian</hi> Organi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Cant; which things were not known in the Primitive Church.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the Venerable Fathers unanimouſly declare againſt the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical uſe of Organs; and therefore, you muſt either Rebel againſt their Paternal Authority, or be content to Knock under, as we ſay. The Church of Old look'd like it Self, a Pure, Holy Virgin; and had no Superſtitious Ornamental Appendages to enhance it's Native Simplicity.</p>
            <p>But Alas! How is her beautiful Face now mangl'd? As ſome of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Ladies, who (tho' Nature has accommodated 'm with comely Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yet) ridiculouſly paint 'mſelves: So ſome of our <hi>Prelatical Tantivies</hi> have ſo miſerably daub'd the Face of the Church with <hi>Organical</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Dyes, and other Ceremonious Untemper'd Mortar, that if the Primitive Fathers were now alive again, they cou'd not know their own Daughter.</p>
            <q>— Hinc illae Lachrymae —</q>
            <p>We'll conclude this Chapter with that excellent Prayer of our Church, <hi>viz. God grant all us, the Kings Highneſs, faithful and true Subjects, to feed of the ſweet and ſavoury Bread of Gods own Word: And (as Chriſt commanded) eſchew all our Phariſaical and Papiſtical leven of Man's fained Religion</hi> — Homily of good Works, <hi>Part</hi> III. <hi>Page</hi> 38.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:39444:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> 
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Many of the Reformed Churches without Organs. Animadverſions on thoſe that have 'm. Several Modern Divines, Church-Men, Papiſts, and others, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> it ſelf, againſt the uſe of Organs in Divine Worſhip.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN the next Place, we'll conſider the extent of this Organical Worſhip, and in doing that, it mayn't be amiſs to lay before you an Account of thoſe Places, where (1.) Organs are not us'd in their Spiritual Worſhip. And (2.) Where they are us'd.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) There are many of the Reformed Churches, and ſome of 'm, the beſt in the World, that never us'd Organs, or any other Muſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their Sacred Aſſemblies and Worſhip. As the Reformed Churches in <hi>Germany,</hi> the <hi>Helvetian</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Proteſtant Churches: Many of the Proteſtant Churches in <hi>Poland, Sweedland, Denmark,</hi> and many of thoſe in the <hi>Belgic</hi> Provinces. The <hi>Hungarian,</hi> and <hi>Tranſilvanian</hi> Churches, and thoſe of <hi>Piedmont.</hi> The <hi>Scotch</hi> Churches. All the Proteſtant Diſſenting Churches, and indeed the greateſt Number of Pariſh Churches in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> Obſerve here, (1.) That the greateſt Number, and ſome of the pureſt <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches in the World, have always been without Organs. And (2.) That the defect thereof, has been no hindrance to the flouriſhing State of thoſe Churches; nay (3.) If we may judge of the Tree by it's Fruit, ſome of the Anti-Organical Churches have been the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently Pious, and have moſt remarkably ſignaliz'd their Courage and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, in the perſecuted Cauſe of Chriſt, and Defence of Goſpel-Simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is the main Thing pleaded for in this Eſſay, in Oppoſition to <hi>pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous</hi> and <hi>carnal</hi> Devotion.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) On the other Hand, Organs are us'd in ſome of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Churches, in ſome of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches, in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> and the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches; In our Cathedral Churches in <hi>England,</hi> and in ſome few Parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Churches, and in the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Churches. But then,</p>
            <p n="1">[1.] As to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Churches; it muſt be remembred that Organs were forc'd upon 'm by ſome Civil Magiſtrate againſt the Conſent of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Miniſters; for at the <hi>National Synod</hi> held at <hi>Middleb.</hi> Anno 1581. and in the Synod of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> in the Year, 1594. 'twas decreed, <q>That they wou'd endeavour to prevail with the Magiſtrates to baniſh Organs — out of their Churches.</q> Nothing leſs than Baniſhment, it ſeems,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39444:7"/>wou'd ſerve their turn. Such clamorous, noiſie, bawling Creatures were not fit to dwell within the Calm, and orderly Territories of the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">[2.] As to the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches; they ought not to be admitted as Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns, for they approve of, and uſe many other <hi>Popiſh</hi> Novelties, which all other <hi>Proteſtants</hi> juſtly abhor and condemn, as, <q>Auricular Confeſſion, the Pictures of the Trinity, ſinging Pſalms in Latin, Crucifixes in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion —</q> 
               <hi>Cum multis aliis</hi>— But what if a Parcel of <hi>Conſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Lutherans</hi> are inclin'd to divert 'mſelves by the inarticulate ſound of a few Muſical Pipes, muſt it therefore follow that <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants</hi> ſhou'd Dance after 'm? As to the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches their Errors in material Things are equally obvious —</p>
            <p>But (1.) <hi>Zepperus</hi> obſerves, that the Organs us'd in the Tranſmarine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches are to Delight People at ordinary Times, when the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God is not perform'd. But ſome of our high-flown <hi>Caſſandrian Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Love a little innocent Auricular Diverſion in their Eccleſiaſtical Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and will not as much as open their Eyes towards the Heavens, till they're awaken'd and rouz'd up by the ſound of an Organical Machin. But that which makes me ſmile is, to ſee poor little diminutive Pariſhes ſo eager for Organs, when ſome of the Richeſt Parſonages in <hi>England</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to go to Heaven without 'm. But oh what a curſed Miſery is it to be Poor and Proud!</p>
            <p>And (2.) He that Writes the late Hiſtory of <hi>Denmark,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An Account of <hi>Denmark,</hi> as 'twas in the Year <hi>1692.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. <hi>3. Chap. XVI.</hi> pag. <hi>233.</hi>
               </note> tells us in Particular of the <hi>Danes,</hi>
               <q>That they're all great Lovers of Organs, and have many very good ones, with skilful Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſts, who entertain the Congregation with Muſick during half an Hour, either before or after Service.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Nay (3.) It ſeems in Dr. <hi>Rivet</hi>'s Time, only Vocal Muſick was us'd in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Service, and ſaith he,<note n="*" place="margin">— Si in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glia vel alibi iis utuntur, id aliis fit horis quam iis quae praeipuo Divino cultui ſunt deſtinatae. — <hi>A. Rivet.</hi> Cathol. Orthod. <hi>Qu. 36. p. 564.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If Organs were us'd, 'twas not in the Hours of Divine Worſhip, but at other Times, and that to divert and recreate the People and not to edifie 'm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">[3.] And as to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Churches; there are Three Things I wou'd obſerve concerning 'm.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Churches that have Organs are very few, compar'd with thoſe that have no Organs at all. If they are ſo eminently uſeful in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, as a mouthing Cathedraliſt Swears they are, there's no doubt but the Patrons and Rectors of our Rich Parochial Synagogues that are without 'm, wou'd ſoon make their Eccleſiaſtical Arches eccho, with the ſound of Melodious and Charming Organiſts.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:39444:8"/> 2. Several eminent Church-men, and other Reformed Divines have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſhow'd their diſlike of Organs in our Divine Worſhip. We'll begin with;</p>
            <p>The Learned Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Opinion about this ſort of Eccleſiaſtical Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. He delivers himſelf to this Purpoſe, <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Singing Pſalms</hi> — <hi>is very apt for the Edification of Churches, but as for Muſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they are more apt to change Religion into Fancies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Duct. Dubit.</hi> lib. 3. <hi>about the</hi> 329. p.</note> 
               <hi>and take off ſome of it's ſimplicity, and are not ſo fitted for Edification.</hi> He ſeems plainly to aſſert, that this ſort of Muſical Service is real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repugnant to ſpiritual Worſhip, which is particularly injoyn'd in the Goſpel. And I've heard many Devout Kirk-men complain, that inſtead of elevating their Affections, it diſtracts their Thoughts, and diverts the mind from being ſeriouſly intent on the Matter Sung. <hi>But alas Sir, you're miſtane in our Organiſts, for they ne'r intended to be Religious among their Pipes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Maxwell,</hi> a Divine of the true Prelatical and <hi>Tory</hi> ſtamp,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In his Book en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,</hi> The Excellency of the Church of <hi>England</hi> above that of <hi>Geneva.</hi>
               </note> ſaith, <hi>We agree with Reformed Divines, that Inſtrumental Muſick is neither a Part of nor a help to Divine or Eccleſiaſtical Worſhip.</hi> Bravely ſaid <hi>Maxwell!</hi> The high-flown <hi>Scot</hi> is in the right on't; and the Confeſſion is the more conſiderable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it's voluntary, and not forced by the preſſure of a <hi>Scotch Boot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cowper,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">His Works in <hi>Folio</hi> Printed at <hi>London, 1621.</hi> p. <hi>371.</hi>
               </note> Biſhop of <hi>Galloway,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the beſt Muſical Inſtrument for God's Praiſe, is an upright Heart:</hi> And in's Comment on the <hi>Revelations,</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Heart is the Harp, the Strings of the Heart are the Affections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The famous Dr. <hi>Lightfoot,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>His Works,</hi> Vol. 11. p. 1060.</note> has a very pertinent Paſſage to the Purpoſe, ſaith he, <q>Chriſt aboliſht the uſe of the <hi>Temple,</hi> as purely <hi>Ceremonious,</hi> but he perpetuated the Uſe of the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue,</hi> ſuch as Reading the Scriptures, Preaching, Praying and Singing of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and tranſplanted it into the Chriſtian Church as purely <hi>Moral.</hi>
               </q> Now obſerve, that Inſtrumental Muſick was part of the Temple-Service, and peculiarly ſo, for 'twas never us'd in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, or in their Parochial Worſhip. And therefore we've no more war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to recall it into the Chriſtian Church, than we have to introduce <hi>Lamps, Dances, Frankincenſe, Silver Trumpets</hi>— or the like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pet. Mart.</hi> in <hi>Judg.</hi> c. 5.</note> (who dyed about Year 1562) ſpeaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this ſort of Church Muſick ſaith, <q>It cannot be lawfully retain'd, becauſe the Auditors are ſo taken with it, that they cannot apprehend and perceive the Words if they wou'd.</q> And therefore, I think it's almoſt as good, for a Man to pay his Religious <hi>Devoirs</hi> to Heaven at <hi>B</hi> — in the midſt of <hi>Roſemary-Lane S</hi> —where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39444:8"/>is heard but the confus'd Rumblings of ſonorous and clat'ring Tongues. Or, for ought I know, his Advantage may be as great, if he ſpends two or three Hours at a <hi>Quakers</hi> Dumb and Silent Conventicle. The Truth on't is Sir, I Love Muſick dearly well in it's proper Time and Place; and Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not to divert my Self now and then, by a pair of Domeſtical Organs, but really I had almoſt as good hear the <hi>Myſterious Humms</hi> of a Parcel of <hi>Leaden-Hall Quakers,</hi> as the loud inarticulate confus'd Noiſe of Eccleſiaſtical Pipes. The one is as intelligible and edifying as t'other: But I muſt not attend my demure Enthuſiaſtical <hi>Quaker</hi> too long, leſt my Cloaths be ſing'd, for he ſmells ſtrong of <hi>Italian Smoak</hi> which makes me preſume there are ſome <hi>Roman Cinders</hi> in his Chimney.</p>
            <p>To proceed. <hi>Wendeline</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Syſt. Theol.</hi> Edit. <hi>Poſt.</hi> p. 1643.</note> ſaith of the ſame Muſick, <q>That the Devil by a Canorous Muſick tempts the Ears of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that it may emaſculate and weaken their ſpiritual Vigor by a ſweeter ſound.</q> So that you may conclude hence, when th' Organiſt Plays on's Pipes there's an inviſible Dancer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zanchy,</hi> on <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.19. ſaith, read St. <hi>Jerom</hi> on this Place — <q>What he Writes againſt this Theatrical Gaudy ſort of Muſick, by which Men are drawn to be more attent to the Melody of the Sound than the Words.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Jewiſh Altars</hi> and <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi> are every whit as lawful as Muſical Inſtruments in God's Worſhip: But I'll not inſiſt upon a <hi>Geneva Cut,</hi> when <hi>triangl'd Inſtances</hi> are ſo much in Faſhion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zuinglius</hi> (the firſt Reformer of the <hi>Helvetian</hi> Church) is very warm againſt this ſort of Worſhip.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zuinglii Act.</hi> Diſp. 2. p. 106.</note> 
               <hi>It's evident</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that Eccleſiaſtical Chanting</hi> — <hi>is a moſt fooliſh vain abuſe, and a moſt pernicious hindrance to Piety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pezelius,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Pez. in Sleid. de Quatuor Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periis.</note> who was Profeſſor of Divinity at <hi>Bremen</hi> in the lower Circle of <hi>Saxony,</hi> in his Notes upon <hi>Sleidan,</hi> calls the Muſical Inſtruments of Pope <hi>Vitalian, the Thieves of Prayer, and the Word Preached.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many more might be added, but I'll conclude this Head with the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Thirty Two Proteſtant Commiſſioners, who were in the <hi>Reign</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. and <hi>Edward</hi> VI. appointed by Act of Parliament to examine and purge all Canons, Conſtitutions, and Ordinances, Provincial and Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, do declare, that they wou'd have all Inſtrumental Muſick as Organs — quite taken away out of the Church.<note place="margin">Reformatio le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum Anglica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum de Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Officiis. <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perf. Tract.</hi>
               </note> The ſame Commiſſion was reviv'd in <hi>Queen</hi> Elizabeth<hi>'s Reign,</hi> but quickly dropt, and to the great Prejudice of the Church has ſlept ever ſince, as the Learned and Reverend Biſhop <hi>Burnet</hi> ſaith.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:39444:9"/>
            <p> The Perſons Deputed to this Purpoſe were, <hi>Cranmer</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Ridley</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London, Ponet</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter, Goodrick</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Ely, Coverdale</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter, Hooper</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Gloceſter, Knight</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bath, Scory</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cox</hi> the King's Almoner, <hi>Parker</hi> of <hi>Cambridge, Latimer, Cook, Pet. Martyr,</hi> Sir <hi>John Cheek, John a Laſco,</hi> Mr. <hi>Peter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cecyl,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho. Smith,</hi> Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> of <hi>Hadley,</hi> Dr. <hi>May,</hi> Mr. <hi>Traheron,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lyel,</hi> Mr. <hi>Skiner,</hi> Juſtice <hi>Hales,</hi> Juſtice <hi>Bromley, Goodrick, Goſnal, Stamford, Carel, Lucas</hi> and <hi>Brook</hi> Record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were the Flowers of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reformation, and Men eminent for Sacred and Polite Literature. And I think the Judgment of ſuch a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable Sett of Men deſerves a Particular Regard. And therefore wonder with what Confidence ſome can pretend to have ſuch a mighty Veneration for our firſt Reformers, when yet they ſo zealouſly defend, and are ſo eager for retaining; what the Old Reformers thought better aboliſht and quite remov'd.</p>
            <p>Thus you have th' expreſs Opinion of many great and good Men againſt your erecting a pair of Devotional Organs in the Chriſtian Church. But if you think, that you can't attain the Supremacy of Bliſs without Converting the Church into an Organical Quire, e'en go on, and let your well-inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Organiſt begin his Anthem of <hi>O be joyful</hi> — while the reſt of the Pariſh are devoutly Praying, like 'mſelves, <hi>From all blindneſs of Heart, from Pride, Vain-Glory, and from all the Deceits of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil</hi> — <hi>and Contempt of thy Word and Commandment. Good Lord deliver us.</hi> And for once I'll ſuppoſe my ſelf in the AMEN-Officer's Desk, and preſume to ſay <hi>A</hi>—<hi>m</hi>—<hi>e</hi>—<hi>n</hi>—. But before you begin, you'd do well to take Advice from thoſe that are able to give it, and who more fit to Counſel you in this Grand Affair than,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Church of</hi> England it ſelf, whoſe Judgement comes next to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, and if you'll not be advis'd by her, for my Part I ſhall give you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as a pack of obſtinate Sons of the Church. But what ſaith the <hi>Church of</hi> England? Why, to be brief, She utterly Condemns the Uſe of Organs in Divine Worſhip, as unlawful, and Thanks God She was rid of 'm in the Infancy of the Reformation; as appears by the following Paſſage out of her Homilies — <hi>Alas Goſſip (ſaid a Woman to her Neighbour) What ſhall we do at Church? Since all the Saints</hi> (or Images) <hi>are tak'n away; ſince all the goodly ſights we were wont to have are gone;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Book of Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the Time and Place of Prayer. <hi>Part II.</hi> p. <hi>131. Lond.</hi> Prinsed <hi>1621.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſince we cannot hear the like Piping, Singing, Chanting, and playing upon the Organs that we cou'd hear before</hi> — To this the Church ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gravely Replies, <hi>But dearly Beloved, we ought greatly to rejoice and give God thanks, that our Churches are deliver'd out of all thoſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39444:9"/>things which diſpleaſed God ſo ſore and filthily defil'd his Holy Houſe</hi> —.</p>
            <p>Take Notice here, (1.) That 'twas the Opinion of the <hi>Church of</hi> England <hi>in</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> days, that <hi>Organs</hi> — in Churches did greatly diſpleaſe God. And are they more acceptable in God's account now? Or are our Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Engineers grown more wiſe than their famous Anceſtors? (2.) That <hi>Organs</hi> — did <hi>filthily defile God's Houſe;</hi> and therefore ſhe thanks God for the removal of this Organical defilement among other Superſtitions. But leaſt you ſhou'd Queſtion the Authenticalneſs of the good Old Homilies, and to look upon the Evidence as weak and impertinent; I'll add, (3.) That the <hi>Thirty Fifth Article of the Church of</hi> England, confirms the Doctrine of the Homilies, as good, ſound, and wholeſome. Whoever therefore aſſerts this New, or rather Old <hi>Romiſh</hi> mode of Worſhip by Organs, directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts the Judgment of the Renowned Church of <hi>England,</hi> And yet theſe <hi>Organical Hot-ſpurs</hi> wou'd be thought her only true Sons, tho' at the ſame time they publickly and cotumaciouſly Rebel againſt her Maternal Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The Church of <hi>England</hi> in another place ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">— Of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies why ſome be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht, and ſome retain'd in the Preface part of the Common Prayer.</note> 
               <hi>That ſome Ceremonies enter'd into the Church by indiſcreet Devotion, and ſuch a Zeal as was without Knowledge. And for becauſe they were winked at in the beginning, they grew daily to more and more abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which not only for their unprofitableneſs, but alſo becauſe they have much blinded the people, and obſcur'd the Glory of God, are worthy to be cut away and clean rejected:</hi> — Injenuous Confeſſion <hi>Monſtrum horrendum</hi> — The Mother and Children ſo very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like! What pitty is it that ſo Excellent a Mother ſhou'd have ſuch a dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate Brood — but <hi>corruptio optimi, peſſima.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">[4.] As to the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Churches, I ſhall only declare the Sentiments of ſome of their learned Men touching the concern in debate. We'll begin,</p>
            <p n="1">1. With <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Inſtrumenta Muſica ſicut Cytharas — non aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it Eccleſia in Divinas laudes nè vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur judaizare — <hi>Aquin.</hi> Sum. <hi>2</hi>a. <hi>2</hi>ae. Qu. <hi>91.</hi> Art. <hi>2.</hi> Obj. <hi>4</hi> ta.</note> who liv'd about the Year 1270, he tells us that Organs were not receiv'd into the Church, in his time. <q>The Church (ſaith he) does not take Muſical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments into the Divine Praiſes, leaſt it ſhou'd ſeem to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daize.</q> And it's obſervable that Cardinal <hi>Cajetan</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Notandum tempore <hi>Thomae</hi> — <hi>Cajet.</hi> in eund. loc ſum <hi>Tho. Aquin.</hi>
               </note> upon <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> ſaith, <hi>Take notice that in the times of</hi> St. <hi>Thomas the Church made no uſe of Organs.</hi> And <hi>Gregory de Valentia</hi> is of the ſame Opinion. It's manifeſt from hence that the <hi>Gallican</hi> Churches which boaſt ſo much of Antiquity, had no Organs in their Churches about 500 Years ago.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Stamp look upon Organs to be really prejudicial to the Devotion of the Holy Church tho' they may accidentally excite the Mind.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:39444:10"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> (who was Counſellor to <hi>Charles</hi> the V. and a <hi>Papiſt</hi> as appears by his Reflections on <hi>Luther</hi>) vehemently<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Vanitate Scient.</hi> Cap. 6. &amp; 17.</note> declaims againſt Organs as abus'd <hi>ad fornicariam pruriginem,</hi> and <hi>filling the Church with ſuch a loud noiſe that the Worſhippers can neither hear nor attend to what is ſpoken:</hi> He looks upon Church-Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to be a <hi>Lecherous</hi> licentious ſort of Devotion, and reſents it ill that the <hi>Holy Myſteries ſhou'd be chanted out by a Company of wanton Muſicians who're hir'd with a great Summ of Money</hi> —<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>. And <hi>Aquinas</hi> in th' above quoted Queſtion,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin.</hi> Sum 2a. 2ae. <hi>Qu. 91.</hi> Art. <hi>2.</hi> Reſp. 4ta. ad 4t. Objectionem.</note> ſaith out of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
               <q>That thoſe ſort of Muſical Inſtruments, do rather Create in the Mind a ſenſual Delectation, than Form in the Mind a good Diſpoſition.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Another Learned <hi>Papiſt,</hi> who reſolv'd not t'approve all he ſaw and heard in the <hi>Romiſh Synagogue,</hi> ſaith in theſe Words. <q>Let a Man be a greater Worldling than <hi>Craſſus,</hi> a greater Reviler than <hi>Zoilus,</hi> yet is he accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Devout Man, becauſe he Sings Service well, tho' he underſtands no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it — Nor are they Content with this, but we have alſo brought into Churches, a Laborious and Theatrical Muſick, a tumultuous pratling of divers Voices, ſuch a one as I think was ne'r heard upon any Stage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Romans</hi> or <hi>Graecians</hi> — All Places roar with Pipes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eras. in</hi> 1 Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. <hi>Cap.</hi> 14.</note> Trumpets, Cornets, Dulcimers, and with theſe Mens Voices are mixt; Love-Songs, and Filthy Songs (to which Whores and Mimicks Dance) are heard. People run to Church as to a Stage to tickle their Ears, and for this uſe are bred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſts and maintain'd at great Charge — A Rabble of ſordid and light Perſons is bred, and the Church is loaded with their maintenance, and that too for a peſtilent Imployment. How many poor People that are ready to famiſh might be maintain'd with the Salaries of theſe ſinging Men?</q>
            </p>
            <p>It's remarkable how our Author ſaith, that People came to Church as to a Stage-play, and <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> ſaith, they went away ordinarily as ſoon as th' Muſick (for which alone they came) was over. And it's well if th' Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Part of Mankind be reform'd in our Days. Now Sir, ſhall Proteſtants declare ſo vehemently for th' uſe of theſe Eccleſiaſtical Whiſtles, when even <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> 'mſelves condemn 'm as Enemies to ſpiritual Devotion? And thoſe of 'm that Dance after theſe Pipes, how do they laugh at us for being their filly Apes. It's to me unaccountable, that there ſhou'd be any <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants,</hi> who in ſpite of Scripture, Reaſon, Antiquity, and th' Church it ſelf, I ſay, in ſpite of all theſe, will yet be the Pope's Baboons and expoſe th' <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reformation to the Jears of Jeſuits, Prieſts, and Fryers, who deride us ſadly for this notorious Piece of Religious Mimickry.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39444:10"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Organ Worſhip an improper Method to correſpond with the End of Religion. The Grand Organical Objection, conſider'd and anſwer'd. The ill Conſequence and the pretended good Effects of Religious Organs examin'd. Th' Erecting Organs in a Parochial Church — againſt th' Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, and an unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Charge to a Pariſh. Organs rob the Poor. Concluſion.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>PRay Sir make your Conſcience <hi>Chancellor</hi> in the Cauſe, and tell me whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you really think the Heart-ſearching God is pleas'd with ſuch Theatrical Pomp, and noiſie Oſtentation in his Worſhip? Or whether your Organical Chanting will recommend your Devotion any whit the more unto a Holy God? Will that which tickles our itching Ears, be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Melody in th' Ears of th' Eternal Being? Will he be affected with that which pleaſes our diſtemper'd Fancies? What, has th' Almighty great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er reſpect to the artificial ſound of an Organ-pipe, than to the dolorous Crys of a penitent Sinner? To affirm any ſuch thing, wou'd be wickedly to repreſent Almighty God, as if he were tinctur'd with the Vanity of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Mortals.</p>
            <p>It may be there are ſome Superſtitious <hi>Fops,</hi> and empty <hi>Noddies,</hi> that may admire and applaud a Worſhip dreſt up <hi>Ala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>node de Rome, de Spain, de Portugal,</hi> (I had almoſt forgot St. <hi>Germans En lay</hi>) with the glitt'ring Ornaments of gaudy Ribbons, and tow'ring Top-knots, but I'm ſure wiſe and devout <hi>Proteſtants</hi> that know better things, will Pitty their Childiſh Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, and Laugh at their Ridiculous Fooleries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> Reprimands the <hi>Heathens</hi> ſeverely, <q>for believing that their Gods did love what they affected,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lactant. Inſtit.</hi> Lib. 2. Cap. 7.</note> and for believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their Temples had ſo much the more Majeſty, by how much they were gay and adorn'd. So the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Church Images, Precious Veſtures,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hom. againſt the Peril of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol. and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious decking of Churches. <hi>Part I. p. 12.</hi>
                  </note> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Glittering Ornaments</hi> of the Church; ſaith, they've no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all profited ſuch as were Wiſe and of Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but have greatly hurt the ſimple and unwiſe, occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'm thereby to commit moſt horrible Idolatry.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection,</hi> But Organs are <hi>helps to Devotion.</hi> You muſt know Sir that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally we're a Parcel of dull Souls, eſpecially at Church, and the Senſes of too many of us are extreamly ſtupify'd by <hi>Banly Opiats,</hi> that the moſt charming Magick in our Rubrick can't poſſibly revive us; and therefore have Thought
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39444:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>of this Organical Expedient to New-vamp our Devotion. For, the Truth on't is, we're e'en tir'd (and I believe the moſt laborious Plow-man or Ditcher in the Pariſh, wou'd not like it as hard as the Times are) to be ſerv'd with Coleworts all the Year round, and therefore we're fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to get a few Eccleſiaſtical Dainties to revive our drooping Spirits.</p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer in theſe following Particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>(1.) The Learned Biſhop <hi>Burnet</hi> ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Biſhop <hi>B</hi>'s. Abridg. of the Hiſt. of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Edit. <hi>2. Preface</hi> p. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>All the helps to Devotion, that the Goſpel offers are in ev'ry one's Hands.</hi> But Organs are not in ev'ry Bodies Hands, and therefore accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Judgment are no helps to Devotion.</item>
               <item>(2.) I muſt needs ſay, that's e'en a ſad lame Devotion, that ſtands in need of a few tweedling Organ-pipes to make it more brisk and lively. Methinks by th' Air of this Objection your Organical Friends want a little Bottl'd Ale, or a Dram of the Cask, but becauſe the Kirk-Wardens will not allow the Temple to be turn'd into a Tipling-Houſe, therefore you muſt have ſomething elſe for that Time, to elevate your depreſſed Minds; and nothing like to a pair of rouſing melodious Organs.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Surely Sir, we've a great many <hi>Phlegmatich Sinners</hi> among us, and I wiſh there be no <hi>Saulites</hi> in the <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> when there's ſuch violent Application made to <hi>Muſical Diverſions</hi> and <hi>Organical Plays.</hi> The Learned <hi>Parous</hi> ſaith, that, <hi>to Advocate for Organs is impertinent,</hi> for adds he, <q>In the Church the Mind is not to be rais'd to God, and ſpiritual Joy, by Pipes, Trumpets, and Timbrels (which God of old indulged his People who were of a ſtiff neck and dull ſtupid Mind) but by ſacred Sermons,<note place="margin">Hinc vero Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganorum uſum templis velle defendere inep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt— In Eccleſia ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citandus eſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; loetitiam non tibiis, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis tympanis (quod veteri durae cervicis &amp; ſtupidae mentis populo Deus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim indulſit) ſed ſacris concioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Pſalmodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is &amp; Hymnis. <hi>Com.</hi> in <hi>1 Cor. 14.7. p. 599.</hi> Edit. 2de.</note> Pſalms and Hymns — Obſerve here, (1.) He calls the <hi>Votaries</hi> of Organs a fooliſh impertinent ſort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</q> And it's no wonder, he brands 'm with ſo black a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, when they leave the Subſtance and run after the Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. When an Heir is impleaded for an Idiot, the Judge commands an Apple — or a Counter — with a Piece of Gold — to be ſet before him, to try which he'll take; and if he takes th' Apple, or the Counter, and leave the Gold; he's then caſt for a Fool: For he knows not the value of things, or how to make a true Election. And are not our Organical Sinners thus fooliſh? For when Bugels, and Diamonds, Braſs Counters, and Gold are ſet before 'm; they leave the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds and Gold of the Goſpel, and pleaſe 'mſelves with the Ceremonious Toys, and Baubles of an abrogated Law. And
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39444:11"/>(2.) He Aſſerts, that ſpiritual Joy is not rais'd by Muſical Inſtruments; and if ſo, then the Church-uſe of Organs is notoriouſly impertinent. (3) He adds, that the <hi>Jews</hi> were indulg'd in the uſe of 'm, becauſe they were a ſtiff-necked ſtupid People. Now, methinks, our Organical Neighbours look as like a parcel of Stubborn <hi>Jews,</hi> as one Egge to another; and ſome of 'm are as ſtiff-necked Bigots, as ever the <hi>Jeruſalem Jews</hi> were when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieg'd by <hi>Veſpaſian;</hi> and as an evidence of their more than <hi>Jewiſh Bigotry,</hi> they make Idols of Ceremonies, and had rather ſee the Kingdom run down with <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Blood than Part with the leaſt Hemm of a <hi>Conſecrated Frock;</hi> but they (forward Souls) will ſtep more than half way o're th' Hedge to meet his <hi>Holineſs of</hi> Rome.</p>
            <p>But leſt you ſhou'd think I'm a little too uncharitable, give me leave to tell you, I deliver not my own Judgment, but that of the <hi>Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land her ſelf, for ſhe in her Diſcourſe of Ceremonies — has this remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Paſſage — <hi>And whereas in this our Time, the Minds of Men are ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, that ſome think it a great Matter of Conſcience to depart from a piece of the leaſt of their Ceremonies, they be ſo addicted to their Old Cuſtoms</hi> —</p>
            <p>And that you have a Pack of dull Animals in the Prelatical Conſtitution, you acknowledg'd to me in your <hi>Fourth Letter,</hi> wherein you added, <q>That theſe were the Poor Creatures that ſtood in need of a little Organical Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and 'twas an Act of Charity to relieve 'm;</q> and you may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that in my Anſwer, I reſolv'd this, and a great many other <hi>Parochial</hi> Irregularities into the Ignorance, ill Morals, and ill Conduct of ſome <hi>digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Drones</hi> among us, who labour more for the <hi>Fleece</hi> than for the <hi>Flock.</hi> But then Sir, I made a Diſtinction, and in particular aſſur'd you, that the Parſon of my own Pariſh, was a Man of good Morals, good Learning and of great Pains; and therefore was juſtly excluded from thoſe Cenſures. If all that wear his Coat had but his Learning, and exemplary Life; I'm ſure our Critical Adverſaries wou'd have no grounded occaſion to hit us i'th' Teeth with the Scandals of Clergy-Men.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) If Organs may be us'd in Church-Worſhip, to elevate our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Why mayn't other Inventions be added, that may as effectually An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the ſame End? I'll grant you as much as you deſire, that Muſick may accidentally elevate a drouſie Mind; but ſo do a great many other things, as a Skeleton, a Bloody Lamb, Devotional Images and Pictures, and the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſix, if you're i'th' Humor to believe <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Romans;</hi> but muſt they therefore be brought into Church, and made a Part of the Ceremonial Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice? <hi>Riſum teneatis</hi> —</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Are Organs helps to Devotion? The <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay the ſame of their <hi>Images, Crucifixes, Lighted Candles,</hi> and all the ſtupendous Relicks menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd in their Celebrated <hi>Legends.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:39444:12"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> makes a hideous Clamour about's <q>Altars, Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Images,<note place="margin">Apud nos Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria, Cruces, Imagines—</note> Relicks and pictur'd Walls, <hi>thoſe are they,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that ſtir up Perſons to Piety.</hi>
               </q> This is the very Language of our Organical Votaries: By which we may Conjecture, that there's a Snake in the Graſs, for they can't plead for an Organ, or Chant out an Eccleſiaſtical Ode, but th' Old Cardinals Cant muſt be the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Song, and then off it go's with a Bongrace.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, they don't adore th' Image, but only uſe it as a viſible medium as they do Organs,<note place="margin">Ne Imagini quidem Chriſti in quantum eſt lignum Sculp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ulla datur reverentia. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas.</hi>
               </note> by which they Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Inviſible God; and yet we count that Idolatry in 'm, and Pray Sir, are not our Organical Worſhippers equally Guilty? Or is that a Vertue in our Members of th' <hi>Engliſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church, which is a Vice in the <hi>Panders</hi> of the painted <hi>Jezabel</hi> of <hi>Rome?</hi> And upon the ſame pretence as Organs are introduc'd into Divine Service, the Walls of our Church may be fill'd with devotional Pictures to enflame th'. Affections; in fine what's there that an <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant</hi> can ſay for an Organ, which an <hi>Italian</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt will not ſay for a Crucifix and Carved Images, the darling Inſtruments of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Devotion: The Truth on't is, for you t' aſſert that by th' uſe of Organical Melody your Affections are rais'd to the Supream Being, is in Effect the ſame, as if a Woman ſhou'd ſay, that ſhe keeps Company with another Man to raiſe her Affections to her abſent Husband.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) By this Objection, you acknowledge not only the grievous lameneſs of your Church-Devotion, but th' ineffectualneſs of the Common-Prayer to Cure it; otherwiſe, what need of conſulting the <hi>Vitalian Oracle?</hi> This puts me in mind of <hi>Serenus Creſſy,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Mr. <hi>B.</hi> about <hi>Baker</hi>'s Book.</note> 
               <q>who forſook the Church of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe <hi>(as be ſaith)</hi> he found no ſpiritual Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in't. And <hi>Hutchinſon, alias, "Berry</hi> the Prieſt Writes,<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>B.</hi> Cain <hi>and</hi> Abel, <hi>p.</hi> 134, 135.</note> That the moſt of ſerious Godlineſs among <hi>Engliſh Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> is found among thoſe call'd <hi>Puritans.</hi>
               </q> But I'm ſure, the Modern <hi>Puritans</hi> have more Charity for their Friends and Neighbours, than th' Objector's Catholick Friend has.</p>
            <p>Here's then a very conſiderable defect acknowledged; that the Prayers and Preachments of the Church are liveleſs and dull, for the Affections of theſe Organical Gentlemen are not excited by them, but that we mayn't always be dull and drouſy; her's a Muiſical expedient thought upon, and the Church-Worſhip ſhall be turn'd into a Stage-diverſion, and an Artificial contrivance: and which (I think) ſhou'd it univerſally prevail, will trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all Religion into <hi>meer Mechaniſm.</hi> However, I am glad to hear your languiſhing Devotion is of th' mending Hand; and that you are reſolv'd to ſhake off that Eccleſiaſtical Ruſt, which your Affections have contracted for the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39444:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>want of rouſing and powerful <hi>Pulpiteers.</hi> But oh the ſtrange Effects of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan-Pipes! What charming influence have they on dull and Melancholly Souls! And now therefore, who more happy than the Inhabitants of Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Pariſhes? By conſecrated Bells, they can drive away the Infernal Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goblins, (if they have but Faith enough to Believe what a <hi>Spaniſh Jeſuit</hi> will Swear to be true) and by the help of a pair of Melodious Organs, they may Conjure not only the lazy and Eſs-hole, but all the Calviniſtical Pariſhioners to Church, and ſo their Pews ſhall be as throng as three in a Bed.</p>
            <p>This puts me in Mind of a certain Philoſopher, who complain'd that when he ſpake <hi>Soberly</hi> to the People, they gave him no Audience but play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on's <hi>Pipes</hi> Multitudes floct after him.</p>
            <p>Oh rare Melody! What pity it's all our Parlors are not Converted into ſo many pompous Theatrical Quires; and that all our Bairnes and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are not train'd up in this Organical way. What more revicing than a Canonical Conſort of Muſick! What ſtrange and wonderful feats have been perform'd by the Melodious charms of Muſical Pipes.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the ſweet <hi>Syrens</hi> that charm'd the famous <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> and's Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. And <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> tells us, that by the Art of Muſick the pain of the Hip-Gout has been cur'd. Here's good news to our Gouty-Pariſhioners; if they can but make ſhift to creep to Church and lay their left Ear to the leading Organ-Pipe, the Cure is Effected, only they muſt be ſure to pay the Piper, for Money is all — Nay <hi>Zenocrates</hi> cur'd Mad-Men by the means of Muſick. Well then, if you'l be adviſed by a Friend; ſend your Organi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Muſick to <hi>New-Bedlam,</hi> and firſt try the experiment there, for I'm ſure there are many in that diſmal Place that want help: Particularly two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn Church Parſons, Mr. <hi>Pr—d.</hi> Who you'l find 'ith Tenth Figure. And Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> who was put in but few Months ago by my Lord Mayor upon the Requeſt of his Grace of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> as the publick News told us. I'd have you make tryal of skill on 'm, for a good pair of Organs are an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Catholicon; and therefore don't deſpair of ſucceſs. And when you've turn'd <hi>Bedlam</hi> into a <hi>Colledge of Wiſdom,</hi> I do aſſure you, I'll heartily joyn Hand and Heart with you, and be the moſt forward in the Croud to Cry, Oh happy Cathedraliſts! And what mighty Advantage have thoſe that dwell near a Cathedral or an Organical Church! Where a Man Ears ſhall be conſtantly regail'd with Harmonious Melody, and the Health of the Body ſecur'd by the ſecret Charms of Canonical chanting: And what is more (for we've reſerv'd the beſt Wine till laſt) the ſweet and Melodious ſound of the Pipes (eſpecially if they be conſecrated) will Effectually diſpel all gloomy Thoughts out of your Minds, and you ſhall be as Merry as forty Beggars in a Barn, and never fall any more into the Quagmire of Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly and madneſs. But after all the Patriarchs of St. <hi>Davids,</hi> and St. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaph,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:39444:13"/>muſt confeſs that the charming Melody of Organs has not been able to preſerve the Sacred Quire from the great Plague of <hi>Simony.</hi> But both Church and State have honorably Acquitted 'emſelves from this Guilt, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Criminals to the Righteous and publick Cenſure of the Law.</p>
            <p>But pray Sir, to be ſerious, upon what bottom do your Friends and you go? I've been told you can't regularly Erect a pair of Organs in your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Church, unleſs you be Authoriz'd by ſome juſt Power; either by the King, Parliament, Convocation, Canons, or Rubrick. And if you're not authoriz'd by theſe or ſome or one of 'm, I humbly conceive you're accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to Authority for a breach of the Law of Uniformity. <q>But I'm ſure you've no power from His Majeſty, no warrant from any Statute Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Parliament, nor from any Canon, or any Convocation, nor from any Rubrick in our Engliſh-Common-Prayer-Book, for the ſetting up Organ-Worſhip in your Parochial Church. And many of the Learned are of Opinion, that according to th' Act of Uniformity, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> no particular Paſtor of a Pariſh-Church is allow'd to introduce new Rites and Modes of Worſhip into his Pariſh-Church over and above what are Appointed by the Act of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformity, without a warrant either from a Parliament, or Convocation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> her ſelf ſpeaks expreſly to this very purpoſe in her Diſcourſe, about the Abolition of Ceremonies, Her Words are, <hi>That no Man ought to take in Hand, or preſume to appoint — any publick or common Order in Chriſt's Church, except he be lawfully called, and authoriz'd thereunto.</hi> Pray then Sir, have not your Organical Friends by their appointing this new Model of Worſhip, out-run Canons, Convocations, Rubricks, and Homilies, and travel'd as far as <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf before ſome of their Brethren have crept as far as <hi>Canterbury?</hi> And pray Sir, mayn't overdoing the Rule, as well as underdoing? <q>Mayn't exceſſes as well as defects in reference to the ſame Canon be a real Schiſm in the Church? How comes it to paſs that only defects in Diſſenters are Sins, and yet exceſſes in Conformiſts are ſuch Vertues?</q> Why is't that a Man may advance towards <hi>Rome</hi> and be no Schiſmatick, but yet one glance o'th' Eye towards <hi>Geneva</hi> makes him a damnable one: What is't no Crime in a Church-Man to out run the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable? In a word, <q>mayn't the Statute of Uniformity be violated by a <hi>Supra-Conformity,</hi> as well as by <hi>Subter-Conformity?</hi> And if ſo, your Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan-Adorers ought to be <hi>Excommunicated ipſo facto, and not reſtor'd until they Repent and publickly revoke this wicked Error, As to</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments for Organs, I'm ready to account for 'm if call'd upon —</q>
            </p>
            <p>And as to the Pariſh it ſelf, where theſe Organs are to be Erected: It's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to be generally poor, and not without juſt reaſons, complains bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly of ſome late unreaſonable Impoſitions laid upon't by Lay-kirk-Officers.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39444:13"/>And Sir, ſhall we encourage 'm to add to the Burthen? For you know that the purchaſe of a pair of Organs will be very chargeable. And muſt the Purſes of the poor Pariſhioners be ſqueez'd again to gratify the Muſical fancy of a few Perſons, that are a little more Merrily giv'n than their mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifi'd Neighbours.</p>
            <p>Beſides, will any of our Friends be ſo unnatural to Poſterity, as to entail perpetual <hi>Italian Gabels,</hi> as an Inheritance upon 'm? For you and they can't but know, that a pair of Organs will be a conſtant Charge to the Pariſh; and you've already more Poor than you're well able to maintain.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the Name of the Poor of the Pariſh, what do you mean? Will you bring in the <hi>Babylonian Bell</hi> and <hi>Dragon</hi> among 'm, to devour 'm a live? I've read that <hi>Pharoah's Lean Kine</hi> eat up the Fat Ones; but for the Fat Ones to eat up the <hi>Lean,</hi> is moſt horridly unconſcionably. But thus 'tis in ſome Towns and Pariſhes, as in ſome Fiſh-Ponds, <hi>Five</hi> or <hi>Ten great Jacks</hi> devour all the ſmall Fry; and ſo if things go on at this rate; in a ſhort time we muſt all joyn in Conſort with the Jovial Beggar and ſing, <hi>A beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging we willgo</hi> —</p>
            <p>The poor Pariſhioners muſt throw away their Money upon Organs; when ('tmay be) their Family want Bread at home. Nay, and theſe poor Sheep muſt not bleat neither, tho' ſeverely clipt; they muſt be dumb, and if any of them be ſo mad as plead Poverty, or complain of Oppreſſion, then a parcel of <hi>ſinful Scoundrels</hi> are immediately ſent to rifle the Houſe, and theſe (forſooth) are authoriz'd to turn Auctioneers, and to ſell the Poor man's Goods by an inch of Candle; and his Neighbour for's impertinence is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd over to the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Purgatory, (the moſt intollerable Grievance that the Engliſh Nation this Day groans under</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Notes in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Sarum p.</note>) where he's worri'd out of's Life, by a mercyleſs Crew of Infernal Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts, that feed upon the Sins of the People.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, it's hop'd you're in ſome meaſure convinc'd how you and your Organical Companions, <q>have Erred and ſtrayed from your Ways like loſt Sheep, and have followed too much the Devices and deſires of your own Hearts — for, from the whole, it's evident that Organ-Worſhip, was part of the Ceremonial Law, which is now abrogated;</q> that the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Primitive Fathers, have not as much as a favourable Sentence to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend the Cauſe of your admired Organs, that Organ-Worſhip is a Popiſh Neoterical practice, foiſted into the Church, when Church-Men had proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted 'mſelves to the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Whore; and ever ſince this and ſuch like Meritorious Pomp has been accounted the greateſt Splendor of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Hierarchy.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> her ſelf has born a very ample Teſtimony againſt you, and what will the true Sons of the Church, as they call 'mſelves, have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39444:14"/>no Umbrage of regard to her grave Dictates? To own her as a Mother, and yet to ſlight her Advice, ſhows that you mind your beloved Organs more than your Fifth Commandment. In a forequoted place, the Church complains bitterly of <hi>the exceſs and Multitude of Ceremonies, that the burthen of 'm was intollerable</hi> — Theſe are her own Words. And what will you add more, when your good Antient Mother complains there are too many already? One wou'd think that they that cry up <hi>the Church, the Church,</hi> ſhou'd ſhow greater degrees of Reverence to her Maternal Authority, and not prefer ſenſitive Contentments before their Mothers Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>But I perceive that thoſe who Proclaim themſelves the Sons of the Church (and pray make Room for them, for they be bulky ones, God bleſs 'm) after all, are but a parcel of over-grown Children, that are paſt Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And Children will be Children ſtill, and therefore no wonder, that there are ſo many tak'n up with Childiſh Toys and <hi>Bartholomew</hi> trifles, but one wou'd think you and your Muſical Acquaintance big enough to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to ride upon a Penny Colt, or a two Penny Gelding; tho the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Alcibiades</hi> did once (to pleaſe a Child) Condeſcend</p>
            <q>Ludere par impar equitare arundine longâ.</q>
            <q>
               <l>To play the Fool at Even or Old</l>
               <l>And for a Hobby-horſe ride a Rod.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But if Organs are ſo eminently uſeful, pray ſhall I ask you a few Innocent Queſtions before we part.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Why have you been ſo long without 'm? No doubt but ye are the Men, and Wiſdom ſhall dye with you. But how then comes it to paſs that you did not think ſooner of this Eccleſiaſtical Artillery to mend your cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy Devotion? Or were our Organical Friends born under a Midſummer-Moon? Whether they were or not, I dare not pretend to ſo much Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy as to determine it. But ſure I am, the Lord of their Firſt-Houſe was wonderfully culminant, or elſe it's impoſſible it ſhou'd ever enter into their Pericrany's to advance Folly and Vanity, Pride and Pomp into the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Throne in ſo notorious a manner.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If Muſick in Divine Worſhip be ſo good; why don't you add more Muſical Inſtruments? For good added to good, makes the greater good; and you know two good things are better than one, and the more the Merryer. Ay but nothing compar'd to a pair of Organs: Oh Organs! dainty brave Organs! they're all in all, the very Cream of the jeſt and <hi>Prim'ſt Jannock 'ith oon.</hi> In a word, we've luckily hit upon a Soverain Remedy that'l ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail to rouſe up the moſt Phlegmatick <hi>Endymion</hi> in the <hi>Paroch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:39444:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> 3. If there be ſuch Excellency in Organs, why are there ſo many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes that were never yet honour'd with a Choir of Muſical <hi>Levites?</hi> If they're ignorant, and don't know the worth of this ſort of Muſical Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Then the Beams of the Eccleſiaſtical Light are not ſo diffuſive and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrating as is uſually pretended, and our Parochial Guides are accountable for this our damnable Sin of Ignorance. But and if they be poor, and can't purchaſe and maintain a pair of Expenceful Organs without ſelling their Patrimony; then in the Name of the poor Pariſhes of <hi>England,</hi> I humbly beg and beſeech all Parſons (by what Names or Titles ſoever dignified or diſtinguiſhed) who have their hundreds and their thouſands <hi>per Annnm,</hi> to contribute towards the purchaſing of Religious Organs for 'm, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Annual charge that attend them; <hi>But mum, not a Penny I'll ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it's time to think of parting, for it's late: And beſides, you know it's exceſſive Cold; and that our Conſort of vocal and Inſtrumental Muſick has laſted long; longer than any that has been known in <hi>Salisbury-Court</hi> for theſe Seven <hi>Years laſt paſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pray Sir, Excuſe my freedom, and attribute the Exorbitancy of my Pen, to that pleaſant motion which the very thoughts of Melodious Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick put upon my juvenile Blood. And as to this trouble, I queſtion not, but you'l be ſo juſt as to place it to your own Account, becauſe your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Reverence for Eccleſiaſtical Muſick, and your earneſt Requeſt to me for my Sentiments about it, drew it upon your ſelf; and I hope you'l Love me never the leſs, becauſe I part abruptly, and conclude without Ceremony,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your's Affectionately to ſerve you without the Accent of Organs.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:39444:15"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>A Letter to a Friend in the Country, concerning the Uſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental Muſick in the <hi>Worſhip of God:</hi> In Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Newte</hi>'s Sermon Preach'd at <hi>Tiverton</hi> in <hi>Devon,</hi> on the Occaſion of an Organ being Erected in that Pariſh-Church. Printed for <hi>A. Baldwin,</hi> at the <hi>Oxfard-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane,</hi> 1698.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39444:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
